Hey, Dr. Corcoran, I've
got one for you. What
do you call somebody
with no body and no nose?
Nobody knows.
Wait, what?
You got one for me?
What do you call a company that's looking
for students to understand normalization?
Nobody knows because Mills
teaches it? Oh, brother.
Listen, I got to go.
Thanks. Take care. Bye-bye.
Hey, everyone. Welcome to
Module 2 on normalization. Super
excited for this topic. It
tends to be one of the more
difficult topics of the semester.
But hopefully you've got
your thinking cap on, you're
ready to go, and let's do this.
So today we'll have after class,
and for the online class, module
two, think of video activity quiz.
So you'll take the video activity
quiz to reinforce some of the
concepts that we'll cover today.
And then the equivalent on Thursday
of this week, at least for the on
-campus students, we have lab one.
So later this week after the video
and learning about normalization,
you'll go through lab one. I'm also
excited today we have a great
animation video on normalization and
specifically a new topic I'll cover.
We'll cover after the animation.
But what we've done over the
summer is taken some of the more
difficult topics and put them into
an animation where I can write
word by word and create the script
so that it's exactly the right
structure, format, content that
I want to cover, as opposed
to rambling through a typical
discussion or presentation.
So why do we normalize? If you think
about a spreadsheet we talked about
the first week, a spreadsheet,
you can contain a lot of different
columns. You can contain different
themes. You could have, for instance,
Dr. Sigurd, if she had
more than one phone number,
you could just give her this
next row, leave all of this
blank, and put a phone
number here. That's common.
Sometimes in a spreadsheet, you can put
two pieces of information in a cell.
But none of that is
allowed in a database.
So first, delete anomalies. What
happens if we delete something. So
Reagan is now on our faculty. She
was a former teaching assistant
as a student and then a graduate
student and she finished her PhD.
But if we get rid of Reagan, this
entire row, then we're left with
locker three being destroyed as
well. And so sometimes if you
delete an entire row, then you
lose information and have a delete
anomaly. Or if you just delete part
of it, then you have a bunch of
null values. And as we go through
both 33 and 4330, you'll see why
null values can be problematic and
should be avoided when possible.
As for an update anomaly,
if we need to update the,
apparently they have the same
number, but if we need to update
a phone number, we have to make
sure we update it everywhere.
And in a database, you want to
have as few of updates as possible.
In Canvas even, as we provide
dates in different modules,
when we update the course, we have
to go through and find every time
we put that data and update it or
if we link the syllabus in several
places we have to go find that
syllabus and try to update it and
ultimately we tend to have problems
for a class to have a few problems
not a big deal but in a database
the data needs to be accurate and
then if we have an insert anomaly
we also run into a similar problem
we want to insert just a locker if
we do that then we have some null
values if we want to insert just a
student then we have a bunch of locker
null values and so in this particular
case we go back to that rule of
one or one theme where we will
eventually have what looks like a student
theme and perhaps the arc has a
locker system and so we have a locker
theme so ultimately we break these
tables and that will help to avoid
these update delete and insert or
unintended consequences All right.
This tends to be one of the most
critical topics for the first exam.
And as a reminder, if you're
struggling at all, please come in
during office hours. We're happy
to sit down with you and just write
through example after example. But
that calls for our class cheer.
Chigga, chigga, whole potato, half
past alligator, bim bam, bolligata,
give three cheers for the happy
sequel coders. Are we happy?
Not today. Sequel, sequel. Yes,
yes, yes. Hopefully, after the
first exam, you'll be super happy
because you learned normalization.
Looking back to the prior
week on database principles,
there are a few topics that
are critical for today.
The first one is when
we talked about a table.
Looking forward, I mentioned
this would be first normal
form. So let's briefly look
through this slide from last week.
So we have one theme per
table. We just discussed we'll
have a student theme and a
locker theme and more if needed.
one piece of information per cell
so we can only have one phone
number and by one piece of
information you as the database person
decide what that value is we'll
talk about that in a minute but in
this case a last name is appropriate
a first name we wouldn't put
one cell for full name we can
break it out later excuse me we can
put it back together later we
can only have one row per record.
So again, Reagan, if she has a
second phone number, we can't just
add a second phone number here.
We also can't add a second phone
number here, and I'll show you why
that is in just a minute, and then
one data type per column. So if
this is all numeric, the data needs
to stay numeric. If it's character,
it should stay character,
ideally. Second review point,
primary key, and non-primary key. For
today, you can forget about clustered
index, but key and non-key. A
key is a primary key. It's numeric,
non-repeating, no meaning to the
user. A non-key is just a regular
old columns value. So last name,
Mills, Heinz, Ostrom, that would
be a non-key. That last name
doesn't determine anything else,
so it's considered a non-key.
and then a candidate key a candidate
key as a reminder is any column
that could be used as a primary key
you can forget super key for this
discussion so locker number it's
bait and everything will be based
on the data so locker number
appears to be unique so this is a
candidate key locker serial number is
also unique that could be a candidate
key location is not unique because
we have two locations with A.
And then locker combo in our
situation is unique. So we could argue
that we have three candidate keys,
locker combo, locker serial number,
and locker number. In this case,
we want to take the one that's
numeric, non-repeating, all three
of them, and no meaning to the user.
Locker number tends to
be the best of those.
And then finally, composite key. A
composite key is a primary key that
combines two or more columns. to
uniquely identify a row. We mentioned
bondo, where we would take one
substance and another substance, mix it
up, and then you can paint on a roof.
But there are two materials to begin
with for bondo to work properly. So
in this case, we have a composite
primary key, and that becomes very
important when we discuss second
normal form. So that's a review from
last week that will hopefully help.
and now thinking caps on we move
into normalization in this video
we'll cover the basics and first
normal form and then in a follow-up
video we'll cover second third normal
form and then take a quick look at
quick look at something called
Boyce Cod normal form so the first
new key specific to normalization
is called determination and we look
at two two terms a determinant
and a functional dependency. And a
determinant is something that can
determine the right side of the equation,
which is the functional dependency.
So for instance, in this example
at the bottom of the screen, I
have an item price and a quantity.
So if I have the item price
and a quantity, I can determine
the total price. I would multiply
item price times quantity,
and that would give us the
total price for that item.
If I had in this diagram here, if
I had my social security number,
My social security number would
determine my last name, my
first name, my address, my
zip code, and so forth. So the
determinant determines the
functional dependencies, and the
functional dependencies are
dependent on the determinant.
That becomes critically
important in a moment. Here's a
couple more examples. So if I
know color one is blue and I know
color two is yellow, these are
the determinants. Everything
on the left side of the arrow
are determinants. Anything
on the right side of the arrow
are functional dependencies.
So, going back to second grade,
blue and yellow make, da-da-da,
bing.
Is it green?
Took me an hour to get
that little spinny thing.
So, left side determinants,
right side functional
dependency. The green is
functionally dependent on
both. This would be a
composite, both blue and yellow.
So, this is an example of a composite
primary key or composite determinant,
if you will. on the exam it'll be
confusing at first but everything
is done in letters so blue and
yellow may green how does this look
in what we call a b no p format it's
just a very common way to look at
it sometimes i use a b d p c just for
the name of the little booklet that
we created years ago but in this
case what we're suggesting is if i
know a and b these are the determinants
they're on the left side of the
arrow i can determine n so in this
case as an example you would say a
and b would determine a and b together
would determine n and sometimes
you'll ask well what is a and what
is b and what is n on the exam you'll
just focus on the letters and that
way you don't have to really think
through if i know this do i really
can i really determine it you'll
know from the letters exactly what's
happening so in this case you'll know
that a and b determines n what is
a and b could be anything in this
case it could be blue and it could
be yellow and it determines green.
It could be your student ID and your
course ID, and both of those together
determine your grade. So your grade
is determined on both A and B.
Or just your student number alone,
we get rid of the B, student number
alone determines, again, last name,
first name, address, and so forth.
So that's determinant, functional
dependency. Those are important for
normalization, along with the prior
information that we just discussed.
In this case, student ID
If I know the student ID, I would
know the last name, the first name.
And if this were the database
table, I would know the locker
number, I would know the location,
and I would know the manager
phone. And that seems confusing
because you think, wait, we have
two themes, we're going to break
this out. And the answer is yes.
But if I ask you, what's student
3's last name, you can look at it,
and you would say, oh, Sigurd.
But if you said, well, what
is student ID 3's location,
even though it's somewhat unrelated
you go oh it must be a and
what's their manager phone number
for student three so because this
is numeric non-repeating and no
meaning to the user or mainly because
it's non-repeating it is a
determinant on itself independently
and you can do the same thing
with locker number locker number
determines everything in this
particular case and this when we get to
next week this is our only look
ahead is we will be creating er
diagrams that look something like
this and this is how our determinants
and functional dependencies work
student id is the primary key
it's the determinant and it alone
determines your last name your
first name and your major how this
would look in terms of the a b n
o p notation is a what is a doesn't
really matter but think about
it as student id if you want a
best case or a real case scenario,
but A determines B, N, and O.
B is a non-key, A is a non-key,
and O is a non-key. And without any
additional information, we can't
really tell if this is normalized
or not, but in this case, we assume
it's normalized until we hear
differently. On the exam, the only
way you can tell if it's not is
if, and it'll look a little bit
different than this, I'll show you
in a minute, but if we have more
information, for instance, B alone
determines N, then we can look at
what that problem, what type of
normalization problem that will
be. That'll be in the next. This is
the DROP acronym, and this
is what we'll use in class. I
did come up with a DROP. I used
to have more letters because
there are a few other items,
but these are the main
ones to determine first normal
form. So given an overview,
normalization, you would first
determine if you're in first normal
form. If you are, then you
can look at, are we in second
normal form? If you are, then you
can look at third. Now to be in
second normal form, you first
have to be in first normal form.
So if you're not in first normal
form, you're done. You stop and
you fix it. If you're in first
normal form and in second normal
form, then you can look to see
if you're in third normal form.
If you're not in second normal
form, forget it. Stop, fix it. Same
thing. Third normal form, you
can look at the final one that we
cover is Boyce Cod normal form
at the very, in the second video.
But I don't usually use acronyms
because as you know, you'll go to a
training workshop and they'll be
like and today's acronym is wonderful
and w stands for whatever right but
the drop acronym i think is really
helpful for the exam so here it is
first a data type consistency with
columns that goes back to that table
where if the data type is numeric
all of the values have to be numeric
if the data type are excuse me
if the data type is character then
it would all have to be character.
That's the first one. So the data
type consistency within the columns.
Second one is R,
no repeating groups.
Let me jump back to the slide
before. So no repeating groups.
There are a couple ways to do
it, both in row format and in
column format. In this particular
case, I have a repeating group
right here. Pete Ostrom, he
has a home phone and you think,
well, he has another phone. So
let's just give him this whole row.
That's a repeating group. We're
repeating his phone number on rows.
We can't do that. The other thing
we can't do, though, is I can't
create another column called phone
number two and then add Pete's
second phone number here. That's
also a repeating group. So
repeating groups is just when you
either try to hog a column, an extra
column, or hog an extra row
trying to give them more than one
piece of information. Because as
a reminder, you can only have one
piece of information per cell,
per row, per column, for instance,
not per column.
One, D-R-O, one entry per cell.
And in this example, Sam, no, you
have more than one. So because we
can't have repeating groups, the phone
number can't take another row and
the phone number can't take another
column, for instance, phone two,
we can't just smush them together
and separate them by a So you can't
put two phone numbers together. So
this would be an example of the O,
one piece of information per cell.
If they also had their first
and last name in one cell,
that would also violate one
piece of information per cell.
And I call this the atomic drop,
because how do you determine,
how do you determine what
an atomic attribute is? How
do you determine what one
piece of information is?
Ultimately, that's up to you
as the database developer.
But there are conventions.
So, for instance, on the
left side, if you think
about an, I guess I have
a kind of an atom up here.
In the atom, we have some
protons and neutrons.
And so if you think about
that, the student name,
in this case, we're using
their entire student name.
So that may be looking at
not the atomic value, but
maybe like a molecule, right,
which consists of multiple
atoms. So that's too much,
too much information there.
Last name, perfect, it
looks just like the atom.
So here we have one last
name, one for everybody.
But if we think, well, let's really
get atomic and start using just
their first letter for a column,
that's where you start to get
into maybe like the quarks or
something, and so it's too detailed. So
the idea of the atomic attribute,
it's up to you as the database
developer, it's just what is a
reasonable one piece of information
per cell? So in this case, last
name would be exactly right. That's
what atomic means, it's just the
best value, the most basic value
that you can't divide further,
but by that it means in a database
context, because of course everything
seems to divide further and
further. On the screen is an example
of the data type consistency.
Just as a reminder, within a
column, the data types have to be
the same. So if you're using
characters, you use characters.
If you're using numeric, in fact,
this wouldn't be allowed either.
This would be multi. This would
break the data type consistency
along with the repeating
groups. So that's an example of
the D in drop problem, the
repeating group we've talked about.
On the bottom of the
screen, this is how a
repeating group would
look like on the exam.
So we have table 1, A is a primary
key. We'll talk about that in
a minute. It's underlined. And then
B1, B2, B3, these would represent
columns. But what we're trying
here, perhaps, would be here's
phone number 1, here's phone number
2, and here's phone number 3.
That's not allowed
because what if somebody
has no phone at all? Then
we have a null value.
What if they have 10 phones?
Not only one null value, we'd
have three null values. And
what if they have 10 phones?
This database no longer works.
So we would redesign it so
that it would work for that.
This would be an example of
a repeating group in terms
of the ABNOP format that
you would see on the exam.
One entry per cell, the O,
we've talked about that. You
can only have the atomic value
that you determined. so one
phone number you wouldn't put
the dash there either in most
cases we'll talk about that
a little bit later but most
of the time the application
would provide the formatting
instead of the database and then p
is determined by the underlined one
primary key here student id so we
have a primary key established and
this is the ultimate rule for
normalization for us is the rule that
all determinants are candidate keys.
And I'll show examples of this.
But as a reminder, the determinant
is on the left side of the arrow.
And if it's on the left side of
the arrow, if it's a determinant,
it has to determine everything.
So we'll discuss that.
Here's an example,
ABNOP.
In this case, AB, the composite primary,
determines everything else, NOP.
In this case, all
determinants are a candidate
key, unless if we have more information.
Here's another example.
AB determines NOP.
P determines ABNO. P
determines everything.
So in this case, you can see we had some
candidate keys. P could
have been a candidate key.
AB was selected.
Usually you don't, but in
this case it's a composite.
But as long as P determines
everything, it's a
determinant, it determines
everything, it's okay.
A, B, N, O, P, N determines,
well, first of all, A, B
determines N, O, P, because it's
a composite primary, so we have
one candidate key, which is
a primary key, but we also
have N, and we have to make
sure N is a candidate key. N
determines A, B, N, A, B, O, P,
then it's okay. As an example, looking
forward to the next video, though,
if N alone determines P, did we
have a problem so as long as it
determines everything it's okay and
then finally here's an example a b n
o p a b the composite primary key
determines n o p but in this case n
alone determines p and this is
problematic and we will fix that that
it will be a different kind of normal
form all right i'll pause the video
here and we'll pick up on part two
talking about second normal form
Thank you.